The next of the microcytic anemias
is anemia of chronic disease.
Now what is anemia of chronic disease?
This is anemia that's associated
usually with chronic inflammation or cancer.
It's the most common type of anemia
in hospitalized patients,
and the idea here is that if there is a chronic disease
that results in chronic inflammation,
then there would be an increase in acute phase reactants.
One of those acute phase reactants is called hepcidin.
And hepcidin, what it does is it sequesters iron
within storage sites so that it cannot be used.
So hepcidin has the ability to lock iron
into its storage sites,
prohibiting iron from being transferred to other cells.
So this limits the transfer of iron from the macrophages
to the erythroid precursors.
And if the erythroid precursors don't have access to iron,
they're gonna have difficulty producing heme.
And again, if heme is low, then hemoglobin will be low.
And if hemoglobin is low,
that's gonna result in a microcytic anemia.
So that's one consequence of hepcidin.
The second consequence of hepcidin
is that it can suppress erythropoietin production as well.
And again, if you suppress erythropoietin production,
that's going to decrease the drive on the bone marrow
to actually produce more cells.
Now, one of the things to remember
concerning this sort of sequence of events
is that it actually makes sense what's going on.
Iron is an essential nutrient for bacteria.
They require iron for their survival.
And so when there's chronic inflammation,
the body doesn't know that there's some sort of chronic disease,
like an autoimmune disease,
or that there's a cancer with a little bit of chronic inflammation
associated with it.
Instead, the body thinks that there is actually chronic inflammation
because there is some sort of microbe present.
And so what the body does is it releases hepcidin
to hide away the iron so that the iron is not available for the bacteria.
And that, you know, theoretically would then result in lack of the ability
of the bacteria to divide and to thrive.
But obviously, in chronic disease, there is no infection.
However, the effects of hepcidin are still felt.
And so this is called anemia of chronic disease.
Now, here I remind you that there's a decreased availability of iron.
It's the same story as I've mentioned before.
Decreased iron, decreased heme.
Decreased heme, decreased hemoglobin.
Decreased hemoglobin is going to result in a microcytic anemia.
Now, what are the lab findings going to be?
Well, the lab findings are going to be based on our understanding
of what is driving this disease process.
So, for example, first of all, you're well aware of the fact
that in anemia of chronic disease, there is going to be an inability to use storage iron.
So, if the storage iron cannot be used, it's going to pile up.
And as it piles up, there will be high stores of iron,
and so the ferritin will be high because the stores of iron are high.
And at the same time, any time the ferritin is high,
the total iron binding capacity will go down.
And that's because the number of transferrin molecules floating around in the blood will go down.
And this is sort of the relationship that we've already explained in iron deficiency anemia.
Another important feature or finding will be that the serum iron will be used.
If the bone marrow cannot use the iron in the macrophages, it will begin to take the iron from the serum.
And when it takes the iron from the serum, the serum iron will go down.
And at the same time, percent saturation will also go down.
So, the serum iron will go down, and the percent saturation will go down.
And then finally, there will be an increase in free erythrocyte protoporphyrin.
Again, that makes sense because you understand, now that we have studied a little bit of the biochemistry here,
that heme is made of iron plus protoporphyrin.
And the problem here is the accessibility of iron.
However, there is no problem with protoporphyrin.
And therefore, protoporphyrin will be produced, and some of it will be floating free in the red blood cell.
It will not be attached to iron.
And so, there will be an increase in free erythrocyte protoporphyrin.
Now, let me just clarify one bit of confusion that can arise depending on which textbook you're reading.
And that is that when you consider this sequence of events,
it's very similar to the sequence of events that would occur with iron deficiency anemia.
Remember that in iron deficiency anemia, the first phase was to have a normalcytic anemia.
And then, eventually, as the iron deficiency becomes worse, the patient then gets a microcytic hypochromic anemia.
Well, the exact same thing happens in anemia of chronic disease.
So, otherwise stated, what I'm trying to say is that in the early phase of anemia of chronic disease,
the patient first develops a normalcytic anemia.
And then, as the anemia of chronic disease becomes severe, and I should say, in particular,
as the iron deficiency becomes more severe, the patient can then go on to develop a microcytic anemia.
And the reason I'm highlighting this point here is because if you look in textbooks,
some textbooks put anemia of chronic disease as a microcytic anemia,
and other textbooks classify it as a normalcytic anemia.
And it can actually do both.
And so, I just want you to understand that sequence of events that we've already covered
when we talked about iron deficiency anemia.
Now, what is the treatment of anemia of chronic disease?
The treatment would be to address the underlying cause.
So, if there's a chronic inflammatory state, for example, the patient has an autoimmune disease,
then we'd want to address the autoimmune disease by decreasing the inflammation,
will decrease the production of hepcidin.
And by decreasing hepcidin, we'll then be able to free the iron that's present in the storage sites
and make it available to the bone marrow.
Another important treatment could be erythropoietin.
Remember that in a subset of, remember that one of the effects of hepcidin
is to actually decrease the production of erythropoietin.
And giving exogenous erythropoietin is particularly useful in a subset of patients,
especially in cancer patients.
So that if patients have cancer and anemia of chronic disease associated with that,
erythropoietin can be particularly helpful in those patients.
The next of the microcytic anemias that I would like to discuss is called sideroblastic anemia.
Now, sideroblastic anemia is going to be due to a defect in protoporphyrin synthesis.
Again, go back and remind yourselves that heme, as I've stated many times already,
heme is composed of iron plus protoporphyrin.
And if there is a disorder in the ability to produce protoporphyrin,
then low protoporphyrin would result in low heme,
and low heme would result in low hemoglobin,
and low hemoglobin would then result in a microcytic anemia.
So that's the paradigm that we've established, and of course this follows that.
So let's read what we have here.
Sideroblastic anemia is due to defective protoporphyrin synthesis,
and again that decreased protoporphyrin will eventually lead to a microcytic anemia.
Now, in order to understand sideroblastic anemia,
you then need to understand the biochemistry of protoporphyrin,
and here's where things get a little bit complex.
Recall that protoporphyrin is actually synthesized by about seven or eight chemical reactions.
So there are a series of reactions that are important for the synthesis of protoporphyrin.
And recall that some of these reactions occur within the cytoplasm of the cell,
and some of these reactions occur within the mitochondria of the cell,
and of course these reactions are occurring in the progenitor cells of the red blood cells,
in the erythroblasts.
I don't want to go through every one of these reactions,
because that would get unnecessarily complex for the discussion that we want to have,
but there are some very high yield reactions within this sequence that you do need to be familiar with,
and they are highly tested on examinations,
and of course they're clinically relevant,
because they apply to our discussion of sideroblastic anemia.
Let me go back and create a little bit of a whiteboard here,
and remind you that the very first step in the production of protoporphyrin
is that succinyl-CoA, which I'm going to just abbreviate here as this,
is converted into aminolivolunic acid.
That's the first step.
And this particular reaction is catalyzed by an enzyme called aminolivolunic acid synthase,
also called ALAS, A-L-A-S.
Important to note that ALAS is the rate-limiting step in the production of protoporphyrin,
so that is important to know.
And the second important point is that vitamin B6 is a cofactor for this enzyme.
So these are two important things to be aware of.
The next step is going to be that ALA is going to be converted to porphylbolinogen,
so I'm just going to call it porphylb, P-O-R-P-H-O-B, porphylbolinogen.
And the important enzyme that catalyzes this reaction is called ALAD, A-L-A-D, dehydrogenase.
So A-L-A-D.
These are the first two reactions within this sequence.
Now, the next series of reactions are, you know, there's a series of reactions that occur,
so there's a few more reactions, and then you get to the very final reaction.
And in the final reaction, you know, eventually you're going to generate from here,
you're going to generate protoporphyrin, protoporphyrin.
And in the final reaction, protoporphyrin is bound to iron, all right,
and protoporphyrin and iron are going to yield heme.
So that we are aware of.
The joining of protoporphyrin to iron occurs by an enzyme called ferrokelatase.
Ferrokelatase, ferrokelatase, F-E-R-R-O.
Ferrokelatase is what catalyzes this reaction, number one.
Number two, this reaction occurs within the mitochondria.
So that's important to know, and you'll see why in a moment.
Let's go back to our slides, and then, and hopefully this now becomes clear.
Protoporphyrin is synthesized in a series of reactions.
And important is that the final reaction attaches protoporphyrin to iron to make heme.
And what's the name of the enzyme again?
Ferrokelatase.
And where does that occur?
In the mitochondria.
At the same time, while protoporphyrin is being generated by this series of reactions,
iron is being transferred to the erythroid precursor.
So here's the idea.
You know, you've got this erythroblast, okay?
And here's the nucleus of the erythroblast.
And adjacent to the nucleus is usually where the mitochondria sit.
And so what's happening in the mitochondria, or in the erythroblast,
is that protoporphyrin is being prepared.
And eventually, protoporphyrin's final reaction that generates protoporphyrin occurs within the mitochondria here.
So protoporphyrin is produced in the mitochondria.
At the same time, iron comes from the bone marrow macrophages,
is transferred to the erythroblast, the cell that's producing the red blood cells,
and then iron also gets transferred to the mitochondria.
And when iron and protoporphyrin meet in the mitochondria,
iron then gets bound to protoporphyrin, and that's what creates heme.
All right?
And so that's what I'm saying here.
Is that iron is transferred to the erythroid precursor.
It enters the mitochondria to form heme.
Now let's pretend for a minute that protoporphyrin is deficient,
so that we're not making protoporphyrin.
If we're not making appropriate protoporphyrin,
iron will enter into the mitochondria and will be trapped there.
It has no way of getting out.
And when iron gets trapped within the mitochondria,
it's going to pile up, because iron is going to continue to come in,
so more iron and more iron and more iron will come into the mitochondria.
And mitochondria are generally present all around the nucleus,
so these are going to be mitochondria,
and each of them is going to become loaded with iron.
And as they become loaded with iron,
that's going to create a ring of iron-loaded mitochondria
around the nucleus of the cell.
And that creates the classic cell that's seen within sideroblastic anemia,
which is called a ringed sideroblast.
And so that's what I'm saying here in this particular slide.
Note what I say.
Iron-laden mitochondria form a ring around the nucleus of erythroid precursors,
and these are called ringed sideroblasts.
So here's a classic image.
This is a bone marrow biopsy.
Of course, we would see this in the bone marrow.
This is where the cells are being produced.
And we can clearly see, see this blue color here?
This represents iron.
This is a special stain called the Prussian blue stain,
and the Prussian blue stain is what marks iron.
Now clearly, in this particular case, we see that there is iron
that's accumulating in a ring around this cell.
I'm going to clear this for you so that you can see it.
Iron is accumulating in a ring around the nucleus of this particular cell.
That's called a ringed sideroblast.
Here's another example of a ringed sideroblast.
And it indicates a sideroblastic anemia.
One of the classic questions that examiners like to ask,
they like to show you this picture, and they like to ask you,
where is the iron located?
I just gave away the answer.
The answer is that the iron is present in mitochondria.
That's high yield to be aware of.
The iron is present within mitochondria.
Sideroblastic anemia can actually be divided into congenital or acquired.
It is important to know that the most common form of congenital sideroblastic anemia
is due to a defect in ALAS.
Remember that ALAS is the rate-limiting step.
It is the step that catalyzes succinyl CoA to become amino levallunic acid.
And that is the key rate-limiting step,
and a congenital defect of this enzyme is the most common cause
of congenital sideroblastic anemia.
Again, important to be aware of for the purposes of examinations.
As far as acquired sideroblastic anemia is concerned,
these are also very high yield.
What are the common causes of acquired sideroblastic anemia?
So one important cause of acquired sideroblastic anemia is alcoholism.
Alcohol is a mitochondrial poison.
It damages the production of protoporphyrin,
and therefore it can lead to a sideroblastic anemia.
Another important cause of sideroblastic anemia is lead poisoning.
Lead has the ability to denature enzymes,
and two of the enzymes that lead can denature are ALAD and ferrokelatase.
So a couple things.
Number one, if ALAD is denatured,
remember that ALAD was the second reaction in the production of protoporphyrin.
If ALAD is denatured, that would then decrease our ability to produce protoporphyrin,
and if protoporphyrin is not available,
iron will become trapped in the mitochondria.
And similarly, if ferrokelatase is not available,
ferrokelatase is the name of the enzyme that links protoporphyrin with iron.
And so if iron can't get linked to protoporphyrin to make heme,
to eventually become hemoglobin, to then leave the cell,
iron will get trapped in the mitochondria as well.
And so lead poisoning is another cause of a sideroblastic anemia.
And the third acquired cause of sideroblastic anemia is vitamin B6 deficiency.
Now remember that the rate-limiting enzyme in this biochemical pathway was called ALAS,
ALAS, A-L-A-S.
And ALAS requires vitamin B6 as a cofactor.
And so if there is a deficiency of vitamin B6,
the ALAS enzyme will not function properly.
That's the rate-limiting step for the production of protoporphyrin,
and therefore the patients will get a sideroblastic anemia.
Now what's the common circumstance in which patients get vitamin B6 deficiency?
Well, the important common circumstance would be isoniazid treatment.
And that's a little pharmacology tie-in.
So that patients who are on isoniazid therapy,
they can become vitamin B6 deficient,
and can develop, as a consequence, a sideroblastic anemia.
Now what are the laboratory findings going to be in a sideroblastic anemia?
Well, generally speaking, the way I summarize the laboratory findings
is that the patients, they get an iron overloaded state.
The idea here is that pretend for a moment that this is the erythroblast.
This is the erythroid progenitor cell.
It's the cell that's making red blood cells.
So what's happening is that iron is coming into the cell.
Here's the nucleus.
And iron begins to build up in the mitochondria,
and of course more iron, more iron comes in,
until finally there's just a ton of iron in this cell.
So the cell is getting loaded and loaded and loaded with iron.
Until eventually, iron, because it has the ability to create free radicals,
eventually iron will cause the cell to get damaged and die.
And so when the free radicals are generated by all of this excess iron,
this cell will die.
When this cell dies, a couple things are going to happen.
But most importantly, the iron is going to leak out.
And when the iron leaks out, the bone marrow macrophages will eat that iron.
So there'll be high stores of iron in the bone marrow macrophages.
And some of that iron could leak out into the blood,
then causing an increase in serum iron.
And so that's the way I sort of think about it.
And that's how the labs sort of play out.
These patients have a high ferritin,
because the bone marrow macrophages are going to eat all of that stored iron,
are going to store all of that iron that comes off from the dead erythroid precursors.
And because the ferritin is high, the TIBC obviously would be low.
And then at the same time, the serum iron is going to be high.
And because the serum iron is high, the percent saturation would also be high.
And so I've already explained this, and I think this makes sense.
But basically the key summary sort of phrase would be iron overloaded state.
And by the way, if you're curious, when patients have hemochromatosis,
which is also a disease in which they have an iron overloaded state,
they have very similar laboratory findings.
So hemochromatosis and sideroblastic anemia share the same laboratory findings
as far as iron state or status is concerned.